<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title>Audun Halland - General</title>
    <subtitle>My home on the internet</subtitle>
    <link href="https://audunhalland.github.io/categories/general/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    <link href="https://audunhalland.github.io"/>
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated>2022-04-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://audunhalland.github.io/categories/general/atom.xml</id>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>The first blog post</title>
        <published>2022-04-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2022-04-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        <author>
          <name>Unknown</name>
        </author>
        <link rel="alternate" href="https://audunhalland.github.io/blog/first-post/" type="text/html"/>
        <id>https://audunhalland.github.io/blog/first-post/</id>
        
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I decided to create a BLOG, and this is the first post in the blog.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven&#x27;t thought fully through what the blog will be about. Probably things
that I&#x27;m interested in, care and think about. Probably a large part of it
will be about computer programming.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just made the big blog decision earlier today. But then I didn&#x27;t really know
what to do. I might be a professional software developer, but I&#x27;m not that
great at &lt;em&gt;web&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; things. I had heard about the JAM stack movement and statically
generated web pages, but I didn&#x27;t make the connection that I could actually build
a blog that way! A co-worker just told me. He listed up various framework
that can be used, and of course I went with the &lt;em&gt;blazing fast&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; Rust one: &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;getzola.org&quot;&gt;Zola&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been a Rust user since 2016 when I first heard about the language.
Sometimes at work, but mostly personal projects. Even though I probably
spend most of my time with other languages, I now consider Rust my &amp;quot;main&amp;quot; language.
There could be many reasons for that. I enjoy efficient execution, probably
because of my background in C&#x2F;C++ and mobile&#x2F;embedded. Rust is an intriguing
language to use. There are &lt;em&gt;constraints&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, it&#x27;s limiting my inner desire
to make silly, short-sighted design choices. Other languages mostly feel easy to
master, but Rust is a continuous learning experience. But this is why I love it,
its excellence in closely modelling the complex craft that programming really is,
and that you can&#x27;t ever &lt;em&gt;really&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; abstract away.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this blog will likely have some Rust content in it. Maybe it will contain
something about music too. Playing, creating and listening to (mostly old) music is my
other passion. Perhaps I will import some things written on other blogging platforms
into this blog. Those posts will then predate this post, but this is still the
first post of &lt;em&gt;this&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; blog!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next I&#x27;ll likely have to make some theme adjustments, even though I promised myself
I wasn&#x27;t going to care about the visual style of the blog.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
</feed>
